<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>One trumpet more sounded out of Sion to the inhabitants of the earth which they may take as a warning for them to let Israel go and worship their God after their wonted manner, or else destruction will the Lord bring upon them eternally : and also a few words by way of expostulation with the spirit of Cain ... / given forth by ... John Ives.</title>
            <author>Ives, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45836</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I1107</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34475</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14449707</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14449707</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102372</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45836)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102372)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1061:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>One trumpet more sounded out of Sion to the inhabitants of the earth which they may take as a warning for them to let Israel go and worship their God after their wonted manner, or else destruction will the Lord bring upon them eternally : and also a few words by way of expostulation with the spirit of Cain ... / given forth by ... John Ives.</title>
                  <author>Ives, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102372:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ONE TRUMPET More ſounded out of <hi>SION</hi> to the Inhabitants of the Earth, which they may take as a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for them to let <hi>ISRAEL</hi> go and Worſhip their God after their wonted manner, or elſe Deſtruction will the Lord bring upon them Eternally.</p>
            <p>AND ALSO A FEW words by way of Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulation with the Spirit of <hi>CAIN,</hi> and all thoſe that are found in it, and what was <hi>CAINS</hi> portion in that day, and alſo what will be the portion of theſe Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors who are Succeſſours of <hi>CAINS</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and perſecuteth about Sacrifices and Wroſhip in this our Day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Given forth by one who deſireth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of SION and the Destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of BABYLON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>JOHN IVES.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1664.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:102372:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102372:2"/>
            <head>ONE <hi>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MPET</hi> more ſounded out of <hi>SION</hi> to the Inhabitants of the Earth, which they may take as a Warning for them for to let <hi>ISRAEL</hi> go and Worſhip their God after their wonted manner, or elſe Deſtruction will the Lord bring upon them Eternally.</head>
            <p>HEAR <hi>and fear oh Earth, and hearken what the Lord ſaith;</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>How long will you perſiſt in wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and not forſake the evil of your ways; what is there found in you oh ye Inhabitants of the earth, is not the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of your fathers found amongſt you; Oh what manner of evil was there in your fathers days which you are not found in, ſhall you not receive the reward of your fathers who hath killed the</hi> PROPHETS <hi>and</hi> MARTYRS <hi>of</hi> JESUS, <hi>will not the bloud of all the Prophets from</hi> ABEL <hi>to this day be required at your hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>YEA <hi>verily, and this do I declare in your ears; Oh ye Inhabitants of the earth, that ye may be once more warned and tremble before the God of</hi> JACOB, <hi>who will conſume the wicked and deliver the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives out of</hi> BABYLON <hi>by a way which you know not; for verily the arm of the Lord is ſtretched forth to deliver his poor afflicted</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>who is afflicted with the tasks of the</hi> EGYPTIANS, <hi>and have long groaned under their burthens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT <hi>the Lord hath heard their crys, and deliverance will he bring in deſpite of</hi> PHARAOH <hi>and all his hoſt, for deſtruction and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will he bring upon you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HEAR <hi>ye this ye old men, and give ear all ye Inhabitants of the land, tremble and fear for the day of the Lord is at hand, a day of darkneſs and gloomyneſs a day of clouds and of thick darkneſs, ſuch as never was before,</hi> WOE WOE, <hi>from the Lord God unto the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the earth, who hath ſlighted the groans of</hi> SION, <hi>and have oppreſſed the righteous ſeed, and doth not at all remember the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of</hi> JOSEPH, <hi>but rather oppreſses the afflicted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT <hi>for theſe things will the Lord render unto you vengeance ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you repent, for his Decree is againſt you to deſtroy you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THEREFORE <hi>I ſay unto you all in the fear and dread of the Lord God (who have been fighters againſt the Lord) that you now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102372:3"/>before your time be wholly ſpent, and cleave to the light of the Lord Jeſus, and then will the Lord receive you and give you an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance with the faithful, who are as dear unto him as the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his eye, and cannot bear the afflictions of them, though he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers longer for the tryal of his people, yet this know that he will roar out of</hi> SION <hi>with a dreadfull noiſe, by which the powers of the earth ſhall be made to tremble, and bow before him, for his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is dreadful to the wicked, and who can abide the day of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND in that day will he be a ſwift witneſs againſt the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers, and againſt Idolaters, and falſe Swearers; and thoſe who oppreſs the heritage of God, which is poor afflicted IS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAEL which hath long been oppreſſed by the baſer ſort of people, as PAUL was in his day; unto which truth we bear Teſtimony too, for PAUL was aſſaulted when he came to the Houſe of JASON and cryed againſt by the baſer ſort, (theſe are they which have turned the world up ſide down, and will not obey the Decrees of CESAR, but ſays there is another King one JESUS; and this was the cry in all Ages againſt the truth of God as well as in this our Age (as we may read in the Scriptures of truth, by the Sorcerers, and Idolaters, and falſe Swearers; but the Lord delivered his people and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them all.</p>
            <p>THEREFORE howl, howl, ye uncircumciſed, mad, raging Bulls, for miſery will be your end; for the cry of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is entred into the ears of the Lord of the Sabbath, and a Record of all your doings is ſtanding before the great God of the whole earth, who will judge the WHORE, BEAST, and falſe PROPHET, and caſt them alive into the Lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone forever.</p>
            <p>AND this do I declare unto you who have the name of Chriſtians, but are out of the nature as the profeſſing JEWS was in Chriſts days, who profeſſed the Scriptures which bore Teſtimony of Chriſt; but when he came they perſecuted him and put him to death, but theſe were JEWS outwardly and not inwardly, they had the name of JEWS as you have the name of Chriſtians, but far from Chriſtians nature; <hi>For Chriſt came not to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102372:3"/>
            <p>THEREFORE I ſay as you tender the good of your own Souls ceaſe from your cruelty and oppreſſion, and let ISRAEL go free, who would only paſs thorow your Country, or elſe you ſhall be as ſtubble, <hi>And the day that cometh ſhall burn you up, and leave you neither root nor branch ſaith the Lord of hoſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. I.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:102372:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AND ALSO A FEW words by way of</hi> Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulation with the Spirit of <hi>CAIN,</hi> and all that are found in it, and what was <hi>CAINS</hi> portion in that day, and alſo what will be the portion of theſe perſecutors who are Succeſſors of <hi>CAINS</hi> Spirit, and perſecuteth about Sacrifice and Worſhip in this our day.</head>
            <p>HOw now CAIN? what is the matter thou art ſo wroth, what is not thy offering accepted that thou falleſt out and killeſt thy Brother, what doſt thou intend, or what is the cauſe of thy wroth; ſurely it is becauſe thy Brothers ſacrifice is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, and thine rejected: but CAIN why art thou ſo wroth if thou doſt well, ſhall not thou be accepted; but if thou doſt ill ſin lieth at the door, and the hand of the Lord ſhall depart from thee, and thou ſhalt be a vagabond and a fugitive in the earth, and all that meet thee ſhall ſlay thee, becauſe thou haſt departed from the Lord in ſhedding the bloud of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous about ſacrifice and worſhip; and now CAIN ſad and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is thy ſtate, for thou art driven out from the preſence of the Lord; and it is thy ſin that hath ſeparated between thee and thy God, for the bloud of the righteous cryeth for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and aſſuredly it will be ſpeedily executed upon the heads of the tranſgreſſours who thus fighteth with CAINS Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in this our day againſt them whom the Lord hath raiſed up to offer a ſweet ſacrifice which is accepted of him; and becauſe of this thou CAIN art wroth, and by thy perſecuting with long impriſonments even unto death, the righteous thou thinkeſt to overcome, or by thy acts for baniſhment; but CAIN that will not do, its not thy acts which will affright them nor drive them from the Lord, or the enjoyments of his preſence; for CAIN its neither walls nor Seas which can ſeparate them from the preſence of their God which they now enjoy, but its thy ſin CAIN which hath ſeparated between thee and thy God.</p>
            <p>SURELY CAIN if thou hadſt offered ſacrifice which had been righteous, would not the Lord have accepted it; Yes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102372:4"/>ſure, then what need would there have been to perſecute about it, but CAIN thy ſacrifice is unclean and not accepted, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou art wroth and perſecuteſt thy Brother, which is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible token againſt thee that thou art out of the truth CAIN, becauſe thou art found perſecuting and killing about ſacrifice and worſhip, thoſe that cannot for Conſcience ſake bow to any graven image, which thou CAIN haſt ſet up to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in thy fallen and driven out ſtate from the preſence of God; and this is the cauſe CAIN why thou perſecuteſt them, becauſe they cannot bow to the likeneſs of any thing, but will worſhip their God in ſpirit and truth. Surely CAIN thy puniſhment is great; for to thy offering the Lord will have no reſpect, becauſe thou haſt killed thy Brother, whoſe bloud cryeth for vengeance; well CAIN if thou believeſt its lawful for to kill and baniſh all that cannot for fear of grieving God bow unto thy image which thou haſt ſet up: Then give us an inſtance where ever Chriſt and any of his APOSTLES baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoſe that would not come to their worſhip; which was in the Spirit and in the truth, ſurely CAIN thou haſt no Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from Chriſt or any of his Apoſtles for it, neither can thou give any inſtance from them by any Scripture nor any other of, the true Prophets, except thou goeſt to ISHMAEL, PHARAOH and HEROD, who ſucceſſes thy ſpirit CAIN for HEROD ſought the young Childs life, and PHARAOH perſecuted the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> till the hand of the Lord turned againſt him and drowned them all in the SEA; and this was about ſacrifice and worſhip which thou CAIN art found in, ſurely CAIN, our God is the ſame that ever he was, he changeth not; ſurely he will recompence thee according to thy doings, as well as he did HEROD, PHARAOH, and ISHMAEL, for that ſpirit of perſecution; but <hi>Cain,</hi> what haſt thou done by all thy long impriſonments or by thy acts of baniſhment, haſt thou turned any from the evil of their ways as Chriſt and his Apoſtles did: who won them by ſound Doctrine, no none, but on the contrary thou wouldſt cauſe them to blaſpheme by thy inſtruments of cruelty; but for theſe things is thy day ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which is for the Elect ſake, and a remnant ſhall be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved unto God pure and undefiled, ſtanding upon the rock on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102372:5"/>which thou ſhalt be ſplit, and upon the ſand ſhalt thou ſtick and never remove again, for the mouth of the Lord of hoſts hath ſpoken it.</p>
            <p>Given forth from the true fear and dread of the Lord God, by one who now ſuffereth under CAIN, PHARAOH, and HERODS Spirit, for the Teſtimony of Jeſus which is the word of God.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>AND now you perſecutors who have this Book to Read,</l>
               <l>Conſider it well, for your portion it is indeed;</l>
               <l>That have thus fought againſt the living God,</l>
               <l>Who will confound the wicked with his Rod:</l>
               <l>And you ſhall feel the ſtroak of his own hand,</l>
               <l>Who ſtrives to make his choſen dear forſake their native land.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Wisbech <hi>Goal</hi> 
                  <date>the <hi>14th day of the 6th Moneth</hi> 1664.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>JOHN IVES.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102372:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
